<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-30T11:36:53-05:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Missing Maps</title><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">$25,000 Grant to OpenStreetMap</title><link href="/blog/2017/12/11/osmf-grant/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="$25,000 Grant to OpenStreetMap" /><published>2017-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/12/11/osmf-grant</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/12/11/osmf-grant/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-red-cross-grants-openstreetmap-25000&quot;&gt;American Red Cross grants OpenStreetMap $25,000&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Red Cross is very excited to announce a USD $25,000 grant to OpenStreetMap Foundation for a hardware purchase to support the ongoing resilience of the OSM infrastructure. The funds were allocated towards the purchase and provisioning of a ‘hot’ backup database failover server – which has been purchased and is currently humming along doing its important job! This trail-blazing contribution will ensure that we can recover from site failures quickly and with the minimum amount of disruption for those editing the map. This is a big step forward in platform resiliency that we otherwise would not have been able to make at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Red Cross and OpenStreetMap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Red Cross has steadily ramped up our support for OpenStreetMap since our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redcross.org/news/article/New-Mapping-Technologies-for-the-Developing-World&quot;&gt;first mapathon in to map communities in Uganda in 2012&lt;/a&gt;. Identifying OSM as a source of up-to-date map data crucial to their international disaster field operations, we’ve quickly developed into a major contributor to OSM and support of the Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team (HOT). Most recently through the Missing Maps initiative, to which around 10% of all OSM map contributions can now be attributed. The American Red Cross also supports OpenStreetMap through &lt;a href=&quot;http://posm.io&quot;&gt;app development&lt;/a&gt; and sponsorship of &lt;a href=&quot;http://sotm.us&quot;&gt;State of the Map&lt;/a&gt; conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in the technical specifications of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://hardware.openstreetmap.org/servers/eddie.openstreetmap.org/&quot;&gt;new server&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope more organizations which use OSM data will be inspired to strengthen the OSMF infrastructure and support our great project! If you are interested in donating to the OpenStreetMap Foundation, please get email them at  board@osmfoundation.org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About OpenStreetMap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OpenStreetMap Foundation is a not-for-profit organization, formed in the UK to support the OpenStreetMap Project. It is dedicated to encouraging the growth, development and distribution of free geospatial data and to providing geospatial data for anyone to use and share. The OpenStreetMap Foundation owns and maintains the infrastructure of the OpenStreetMap project. You can support OpenStreetMap by becoming a member, donating or joining our volunteer Working Groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Red Cross shelters, feeds and provides emotional support to victims of disasters in the US; teaches skills that save lives; provides international humanitarian aid; and supports military members and their families. In 2017 alone, the American Red Cross sent humanitarian aid to 26 countries to help save lives in the aftermath of disasters. The Red Cross is a not-for-profit organization that depends on volunteers and the generosity of the American public to perform its mission. Visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://redcross.org/international&quot;&gt;redcross.org/international&lt;/a&gt; of more information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dale Kunce</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Red Cross" /><category term="OpenStreetMap" /><category term="OpenStreetMap Foundation" /><summary type="html">American Red Cross grants $25,000 to OpenSteetMap to ensure the resilience during disasters.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Thank You! – GeoWeek 2017</title><link href="/blog/2017/12/08/TY_GW17/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thank You! – GeoWeek 2017" /><published>2017-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/12/08/TY_GW17</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/12/08/TY_GW17/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you-geo-week-2017-was-a-huge-success&quot;&gt;Thank you! Geo-Week 2017 was a huge success!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello Mappers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your incredible efforts organizing this year’s OSM GeoWeek! In total, we had 230 public events in 48 countries. We had almost 100 extra events this year and increased our country footprint by 6 countries. Together, we added 292,856 features, which is about double what we accomplished in 2016.  What amazing accomplishments! One of my favorite quotes comes from Geneva, where a participant checked in with her event organizer to let her know that she found that “Mapping was mesmerizing and relaxing” and had spent that next weekend practicing her new skill!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would love to hear about your event to help make next year even bigger and better. If you have time, please fill out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScKG9bYHIcPdHSnT3Yf700LC0evzCqs-ihI5rkjaAopdcCMOg/viewform&quot;&gt;form&lt;/a&gt; to let us know what went well, what went poorly, and if you have any lessons you’d like to pass on to your fellow organizers. If you would like to share pictures, please add them with a short blurb to HOT’s Flickr located &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/groups/hotosm/pool/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great idea to follow-up with your participants (if you haven’t already). Here are some helpful reminders you can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If possible, you can be a part of HOT’s 2018 Crowdfunding Campaign to #mapthedifference. Give any amount to &lt;a href=&quot;https://donate.hotosm.org&quot;&gt;HOT’s campaign&lt;/a&gt; - On the site, you can set up a personal Fundraising page to share with your mapathon networks and supporters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign up for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://eepurl.com/bC7JBj&quot;&gt;HOT Newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign up for &lt;a href=&quot;http://communicatoremail.com/F/QTwz9iBiyP0vavUEMRJ6SQ/&quot;&gt;Missing Maps emails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow us on Twitter at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hotosm&quot;&gt;@hotosm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheMissingMaps&quot;&gt;@themissingmaps&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/youthmappers&quot;&gt;@youthmappers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mapgive&quot;&gt;@MapGive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow us on Facebook at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/hotosm/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/hotosm/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MissingMapsProject/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/MissingMapsProject/&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/youthmappers/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/youthmappers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And of course, keep mapping at &lt;a href=&quot;tasks.hotosm.org&quot;&gt;tasks.hotosm.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org&quot;&gt;openstreetmap.org&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, from all of us on the OSM GeoWeek organizing team, thank you so much for your planning, mapping, and continued support!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, 
Rachel Levine
American Red Cross - Missing Maps Coordinator&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Levine</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="geoweek" /><summary type="html">Thank you for your incredible efforts organizing this year's OSM GeoWeek!</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">OSM in West Africa: The Mapping Continues</title><link href="/blog/2017/11/07/wafrica_geoweek/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OSM in West Africa: The Mapping Continues" /><published>2017-11-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/11/07/wafrica_geoweek</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/11/07/wafrica_geoweek/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;osm-in-west-africa-the-mapping-continues&quot;&gt;OSM in West Africa: The Mapping Continues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year ago marked the end of the West Africa mapping project, where over 100 Red Cross volunteers in Liberia, Guinea, and Sierra Leone traveled to over 7,000 border communities to ensure that these vulnerable areas were “on the map” - creating open data in OpenStreetMap that can be used by responders if another epidemic like Ebola were to occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Red Cross project has wrapped up, the OSM communities are growing in all three countries, and we’re excited to share updates about their activities and what they are planning for Geography Awareness Week this month!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huge thanks to the OSM communities in these countries and especially to those who shared their updates for this post: Youssef Bamba, Tommy Godphery, Emmanuel Greene, David Luswata, Patrick Massaquoi, Emmanuel Myers, O’George Stephens, and Tino Toupane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guinea&quot;&gt;Guinea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSM Guinea has grown to a big community of 233 members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the end of the West Africa Mapping Project, the OSM community of Guinea organized 10 mapathons to focus on mapping in Conakry. OSM Guinea has also fully mapped the city of Dalaba in collaboration with a local Youth Mappers chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community also helped with mapping activities farther afield - helping to map in response to Hurricane Irma, the recent earthquake in Mexico, the Freetown landslides, World Malaria Day, and ongoing malaria activities in Zambia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these contributions, OSM Guinea helped to create three Youth Mappers chapters in Guinea and one chapter at Fourah Bay College in Freetown. The community has also trained 73 students in mapping with QGIS and another 65 people in OSM editing tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For GeoWeek 2017, OSM Guinea has planned four mapathons in partnership with the Youth Mappers chapters of the universities of Dalaba, Sonfonia and N’Wéréloré.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For future activities, OSM Guinea is interested to map the rest of the city of Conakry and to start Youth Mappers chapters at Kankan University and Boke University. They are also looking for partners to support infrastructure and services mapping for Conakry, mapping of the Mount Nimba Biosphere Reserve, and computer upgrades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;liberia&quot;&gt;Liberia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSM Liberia has also been growing quickly, and recently reached 425 members. This includes the Liberia chapter of Youth Mappers, which is active in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, OSM Liberia was actively involved in a HOT project that trained and enabled volunteers to map their respective communities, roads, administrative boundaries, and other amenities in three cities of three counties in Liberia; Bong, Nimba and Grand Gedeh Counties. The volunteers were also involved with data cleaning and editing processes under the supervision of the HOT team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For GeoWeek this year, OSM Liberia is working on bringing all of its cells from all regions of the country to host a grand mapathon event. This event will encompass diverse mapping activities which will last for a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSM Liberia is also looking for new partners for activities for the upcoming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sierra-leone&quot;&gt;Sierra Leone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sierra Leone OSM community is relatively new, but has had an exciting year. Fourah Bay College in Freetown launched a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youthmappers.org/&quot;&gt;Youth Mapper Chapter&lt;/a&gt; and the FBC students have continued to participate in mapping activities. Outside of Youth Mappers, the OSM Sierra Leone community has been growing and was represented at State of the Map Africa by Grace Kainessi and State of the Map Asia by Tommy Charles. This OSM community is working towards formal recognition as an independent organization and intends to file for legal registration with the government. Congrats to the OSM SL community for this exciting step!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David Luswata, Emily Eros, and local contributors</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="geoweek" /><summary type="html">Mapping in West Africa continues, thanks to dedicated OSM communities in Liberia, Guinea, and Sierra Leone. Here's what they are planning for GeoWeek 2017.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Building capacity in the Caribbean</title><link href="/blog/2017/09/18/belize/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building capacity in the Caribbean" /><published>2017-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/09/18/belize</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/09/18/belize/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-capacity-in-the-caribbean&quot;&gt;Building capacity in the Caribbean&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the exciting things about working with Red Cross mapping projects is that we endeavor to build the capacity of the community so that they can plan and lead field projects for themselves. The American Red Cross GIS team sometimes trains mappers ourselves, but we are excited to move more and more towards a model of empowering the local Red Cross and other institutions so that they understand the tools available for mapping, the process for designing fieldwork, and the workflow for cleaning and uploading data and conducting analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the spring and summer, we led trainings in Jamaica and Belize that were intended to raise the capacity of local staff and partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Belize, for example, we led a workshop with 18 participants from agencies with expertise in social services and emergency response, fire response, youth and MARP communities, mapping apps creator, and the national spatial data management division. Participants gained familiarity and skills for the main aspects of the Missing Maps approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remote mapping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data collection in the field&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding the ways the data can be used for decision-making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170918_pic1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Workshop participants in Belize, CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants appreciated learning about different ways to collect information and the accessibility. These included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practical sessions which included going into the community and linking drawings to the satellite images by first starting with field papers by tagging with &lt;a href=&quot;www.openmapkit.org&quot;&gt;OMK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exposure and tutorials on various open source applications (websites) and design and used for apps (&lt;a href=&quot;https://opendatakit.org/&quot;&gt;ODK&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;www.openmapkit.org&quot;&gt;OMK&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://osmand.net/&quot;&gt;OsmAnd&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;www.posm.io&quot;&gt;POSM&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discussion and brainstorming of potential uses for other aspects of regional NS preparedness work (eg. VCAs) and emergency management in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trainings took place both in the classroom and during field mapping practice in Belize City and Gungulung.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By participating in this workshop, participants improved their technical skills and also built stronger relationships with one another, which will hopefully enable productive conversations, support, and possibilities over time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashley Schmeltzer</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="POSM" /><summary type="html">This spring and summer, the American Red Cross led training-of-trainers in Belize and Jamaica to build the mapping skills and knowledge of local Red Cross and government staff - here's a quick update of our work.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">IFRC joins Missing Maps</title><link href="/blog/2017/09/13/ifrc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IFRC joins Missing Maps" /><published>2017-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/09/13/ifrc</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/09/13/ifrc/">&lt;p&gt;We are excited to welcome the newest member of the Missing Maps partnership: the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies (IFRC). For those who aren’t familiar, in informal terms, the IFRC is the umbrella organization that encompasses independent national Red Cross societies in 190 countries and helps to coordinate and support these national societies. This is a cross-post from the IFRC’s official announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-maps-is-building-trust&quot;&gt;Building Maps is Building Trust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifrc.org/&quot;&gt;International Federation of the Red Cross Red Crescent Societies&lt;/a&gt; is joining the Missing Maps Partnership. Missing Maps is an open, collaborative project in which you can help to map areas where humanitarian organisations are trying to meet the needs of vulnerable people – creating open data that can be used for planning, awareness, and analysis. Over 33,000 people have contributed 33 million edits to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openstreetmap.org/&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; since Missing Maps was founded in 2014. These contributions have been used to support health interventions, emergency response, and resilience programs. Volunteers, organizations, and humanitarians collaborate in a number of ways: remote mapping, field mapping, and humanitarian activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170913_Missing-Maps-HOT-London-Event-photo-by-Harry-Wood-cc-by-sa-20.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Missing Maps (HOT) London Event, photo by Harry Wood, CC BY-SA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founded by the American Red Cross, British Red Cross, Médecins Sans Frontières, and Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team, Missing Maps connects a global community of volunteers to humanitarian response. Other Movement members also include the Netherlands Red Cross and the Canadian Red Cross.  Some of the mapathon activities initiatives include mapping tasks in support of work of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icrc.org/&quot;&gt;International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nrcs.org/&quot;&gt;Nepal Red Cross Society&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trcs.or.tz/&quot;&gt;Tanzania Red Cross Society&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifrc.org/en/what-we-do/where-we-work/africa/malawi-red-cross-society/&quot;&gt;Malawi Red Cross Society&lt;/a&gt;. Mapathons have been hosted by many national societies including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redcross.fi/&quot;&gt;Finnish Red Cross&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drk.de/en/&quot;&gt;German Red Cross&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.croix-rouge.lu/en/&quot;&gt;Luxembourg Red Cross&lt;/a&gt;. As we grow this program, we anticipate more collaboration across the Movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to mapathons and remote activities, Missing Maps often involves field mapping with local Red Cross volunteers to add additional detail and context to the map. Previous field mapping activities (led by the American Red Cross) have supported measles vaccination monitoring in Malawi, the construction of a water pipeline in Zimbabwe, the identification of vulnerable border communities as part of Ebola recovery in West Africa, and the installation of fire sensors in an informal settlement in South Africa… to name a few. The scope of these projects varies from community-level mapping to larger-scale initiatives; in West Africa, volunteers visited 7,000 villages to collect information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Building Maps is building trust,” IFRC Under Secretary General, Jemilah Mahmood. Engaging local communities and volunteers with Missing Maps provides an opportunity to link our work to more volunteers, including youth and as well as technical audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first IFRC Missing Maps projects to be launched is pandemic preparedness partnership between IFRC Public Health Unit and the American Red Cross. The teams identified 9 countries where we will be taking a nationwide approach for nationwide data layers. We will likely create Missing Maps tasks for areas identified as vulnerable. This project drives at the core of the Missing Maps mission of creating open data for areas where humanitarian organisations are trying to meet the needs of vulnerable people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are active mapping tasks mapping tasks focused on current humanitarian needs. This includes response for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hotosm.org/updates/2017-09-09_hot_activates_for_three_disasters_hurricane_irma_mexico_earthquake_bangladesh&quot;&gt;Hurricane Irma, the Mexico earthquake and Bangladesh floods&lt;/a&gt;. Volunteering is at the heart of all that the Red Cross Red Crescent Movement activities. &lt;a href=&quot;https://nos.nl/op3/artikel/2191845-daniel-24-verleent-hulp-op-sint-maarten-vanuit-zijn-slaapkamer.html&quot;&gt;Hear one volunteer’s story on mapping for the Sint Maarten Hurricane Irma response.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping Nepal floods:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/O0PwZSpEhhc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;missing-maps-partnership-and-ifrc&quot;&gt;Missing Maps Partnership and IFRC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Missing Maps Partnership mission and goals directly align with our goals at IFRC.  This follows our path of “learn by doing” for data literacy skills.  As part of the Agenda for Humanity (Grand Bargain), the Missing Maps Partnership provides a concrete example of participatory engagement (local and global) by creating and sharing open data for humanitarian preparedness and response.  IFRC will facilitate the growth of Missing Maps activities in collaboration with the founding members and members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IFRC’s contributions as a partner are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;National Society Engagement: Support and advocate National Society engagement for Missing Maps activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve Data Literacy:  Encourage Missing Maps projects as potential teaching mechanism for data literacy/data skills across the IFRC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mapping: Host mapathons and promote Mapping (remotely and locally).  Support for mapping activities (advice and tech support)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage Youth Engagement: Volunteering is at the core of the Red Cross/Red Crescent movement’s humanitarian efforts. There is a large potential to support volunteer, especially youth, engagement in the Missing Maps project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We excited to be collaborating with all the Missing Maps Partners and the wider OpenStreetMap community. Stay tuned for more activities. To get started, follow the Missing Maps blog, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/themissingmaps&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/learn/#beginner&quot;&gt;take a tutorial today&lt;/a&gt;. If you are with a Red Cross Red Crescent society and want to learn more, please do &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:heather.leson@ifrc.org&quot;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Heather Leson</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="IFRC" /><summary type="html">We are excited to welcome the newest member of Missing Maps: the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies (IFRC). This is a cross-post from the IFRC's official announcement.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Join us for our first YouthMappers Video Challenge!</title><link href="/blog/2017/09/05/ym-video-challenge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Join us for our first YouthMappers Video Challenge!" /><published>2017-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/09/05/ym-video-challenge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/09/05/ym-video-challenge/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-youthmappers-video-challenge&quot;&gt;First YouthMappers Video Challenge!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce our first ever YouthMappers Video Challenge!  Missing Maps recently surpassed 32,000 volunteers for the program worldwide, and as we continue to grow, we’d love for some of our experienced mapathon hosts to share their advice with some of our newer participants. With over 70 chapters worldwide, the YouthMappers network has quickly grown to include over 4,000 student mappers.  Share your success story with the community by submitting a video!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guidelines&quot;&gt;Guidelines:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please record your video in English, with subtitles in a second (or third!) language if you prefer.  Please keep your video to 5 minutes or less.  Remember that your audience is anyone who is thinking of hosting a mapathon, possibly for the first time, and looking for some encouragement, not just university students!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;please-be-sure-to-cover-at-a-minimum-the-below-ideas-in-your-video&quot;&gt;Please be sure to cover (at a minimum) the below ideas in your video:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First tell us who you are by giving a brief intro to your group (don’t forget to mention you are a YouthMappers chapter!) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mapping software is not compatible with Internet Explorer (IE) (But Microsoft Edge is ok)  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure a bounding box shows up when using IdEditor, if it’s not there try refreshing the page &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure the wifi at your event space is strong enough &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure no local firewalls are blocking needed websites  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring extension cords and mice if you have spares &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using a mouse is preferred  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tablets are not compatible  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mention the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/host/#helper-map-contents&quot;&gt;mapathon support map&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lastly, leave your viewers with encouraging parting words &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-submit&quot;&gt;How to Submit:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please title your video “Tips and Tricks for Hosting a Mapathon. By: Your College/Uni Name” and post it to YouTube. Next, please send an email with the link to rachel.levine@redcross.org with the name of your main point of contact by Friday November 3, 2017. If you need to provide acknowledgements or thank yous, you can include that as text in the description paragraph of your video in the YouTube upload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Videos will be judged by a panel of Missing Maps partnership staff by Friday November 10, 2017 with a winner announced Monday November 13, 2017.  The winning video will be added to the Missing Maps &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/host/&quot;&gt;Hosting a Mapathon&lt;/a&gt; page and added to the Missing Maps &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLRNDLLd1ecy26kF1UguW5Ii7ozetEghax&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;channel as well as linked to the YouthMappers channel.  The video will also be featured as a new resource in our outreach during &lt;a href=&quot;http://osmgeoweek.org/&quot;&gt;OSM GeoWeek&lt;/a&gt; and in the YouthMappers Resource Library (coming soon!)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Levine</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="YouthMappers" /><summary type="html">Share your chapters' lessons learned with the wider Missing Maps community by filming a short 5 minute video on Tips and Tricks for Hosting a Mapathon.  Winning video will be featured on the Missing Maps website.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Stop the spots: Measles vaccinations in Malawi</title><link href="/blog/2017/08/10/malawi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop the spots: Measles vaccinations in Malawi" /><published>2017-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/08/10/malawi</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/08/10/malawi/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;purpose&quot;&gt;Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you grew up in North America or Europe, chances are good that measles isn’t something you’ve ever really had to think about. A measles vaccine was developed and introduced into the US in the 1960s (followed by combination vaccines like MMR); thanks in part to a strong vaccination program, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/measles/about/faqs.html&quot;&gt;public health officials declared&lt;/a&gt; that measles had been eliminated from the US in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For millions of people across Africa and Asia, however, the measles virus presents a very real threat. Measles is one of the most contagious diseases ever known and it is a leading cause of death among children – despite the existence of a safe and effective vaccine. In 2001, the American Red Cross helped to found the &lt;a href=&quot;http://measlesrubellainitiative.org/&quot;&gt;Measles &amp;amp; Rubella Initiative (M&amp;amp;RI)&lt;/a&gt; with a group of global partners. Through country-specific vaccination campaigns, M&amp;amp;RI has helped to vaccinate over 2 billion children and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redcross.org/about-us/our-work/international-services/measles-and-rubella-initiative&quot;&gt;prevented an estimated 20 million deaths&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 10 million people are still affected by measles each year. The American Red Cross is committed to supporting efforts to eliminate the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;malawi-campaign&quot;&gt;Malawi Campaign&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, the American Red Cross supported a measles and rubella immunization campaign in Malawi in partnership with the Malawi Ministry of Health, UNICEF, WHO, CDC, and other M&amp;amp;RI partners. This campaign acted as a supplementary activity to Malawi’s regular public health activities and was intended as a catch-up for children who may have missed their routine immunization. Over the course of one week, the Malawi Ministry of Health delivered vaccines to children around the country aged from 9 months up to 15 years – targeting approximately 8 million children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support this massive effort, the Red Cross assisted with social mobilization in five districts across the country: Lilongwe, Blantyre, Mangochi, Mzimba, and Zomba. Three thousand local Malawi Red Cross volunteers in these districts were trained on key messages and conducted roughly 100,000 house-to-house visits over three days. Volunteers ensured that the households heard about the campaign and provided an opportunity to ask questions about the vaccine and the campaign – providing an important avenue to address the concerns of those who might not otherwise have brought their children to be immunized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Malawi Red Cross social mobilization volunteers in Lilongwe. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a special part of this campaign, the volunteers in some areas also collected information from caregivers about their young (12-23 months old) children’s routine immunization status – asking to see the child’s health passport and looking for a measles vaccination record or mark in  in his/her vaccination history. This information enables us to identify younger children have missed routine vaccinations; in the future this could help partners to follow up with those children in specific to ensure that they are reached by the health system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Malawian health passport, in which parents record their child’s vaccinations. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Red Cross also supported &lt;a href=&quot;http://measlesrubellainitiative.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Evaluation-guidelines.pdf&quot;&gt;rapid convenience monitoring (RCM)&lt;/a&gt; during the vaccination campaign. The goal of RCM is to act as internal feedback during the campaign, to get a sense of whether the vaccination activities reached the target population, or if more efforts are needed. To do this, monitors visit vulnerable areas that were vaccinated the previous day and complete 15 house-to-house visits and 10 children in a public place to check whether all the children in those areas were vaccinated. If a certain target is not met, this tells health officials that they need to consider conducting additional vaccinations in that area. Timely information about the campaign allows the staff to act while activities are ongoing – meaning that there are still resources, staff, and supplies that can be mobilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Red Cross GIS team supported the M&amp;amp;RI field activities by introducing mobile data collection into the house-to-house social mobilization and RCM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-mobilization&quot;&gt;Social mobilization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the social mobilization, we provided mobile phones for 85 volunteers in Lilongwe (repurposed from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/blog/2017/01/24/west-africa-mapping-hub-end/&quot;&gt;West Africa project&lt;/a&gt; and trained them on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://opendatakit.org/&quot;&gt;OpenDataKit (ODK)&lt;/a&gt; Android app for data collection. Half of the time, these volunteers asked households the additional routine immunization questions. The other half of the time, the volunteers did not. This was randomly set within the ODK survey (link to download ODK survey template) and enabled us to compare the additional time required for the extra data collection, which will help the Red Cross determine whether or not the data collection can be done on a larger scale. We also had a group conducting this work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/Malawi_paper_soc_mob_form.docx&quot;&gt;paper forms&lt;/a&gt; as a control group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Prepping apps and settings on over 100 phones. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteers discussed the campaign with each household and then asked a series of questions about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name and contact phone number for the mother/caregiver&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of children in the household aged 9 months up to 15 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of children in the household, aged 12-23 months, with a health passport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of children with health passport who have a measles vaccination marked in it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of immunization record in the health passport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether the mother/caregiver was aware of the current measles campaign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How she/he heard about the measles campaign&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the caregiver did have a health passport for a child, the volunteer also took a photo of the immunization record in the passport. This enables a quality check of the data afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Social mobilization visit by a Malawi Red Cross volunteer in Lilongwe. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of each day, we visited volunteers at central locations and collected their data using &lt;a href=&quot;http://posm.io/&quot;&gt;POSM (Portable OpenStreetMap)&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source offline server that enables mapping and data collection in offline environments. This negated the need for SIM card and data bundles and allowed us to review the data in an offline environment. Data were encrypted on the phones to protect the sensitive data, stored on the POSM servers, and were later downloaded and decrypted with a private key using &lt;a href=&quot;https://opendatakit.org/use/briefcase/&quot;&gt;ODK Briefcase&lt;/a&gt;. Over three days, the volunteers using mobile data collection visited roughly 8,000 households.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rcm-real-time-monitoring&quot;&gt;RCM: Real-time monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GIS team also supported nationwide real-time monitoring for the RCM. As a collaboration with the Ministry of Health, we trained 58 Red Cross monitors and government health staff from across the country on OpenDataKit for RCM monitoring. These individuals supplied and used their own smartphones for the activities, and we reimbursed them with air credit for the data uploads. During the RCM, they collected and submitted the monitoring results, which fed into an interactive dashboard that displayed the results in real-time. Over the course of the week-long campaign, 73 monitors in 22 districts conducted 440 RCM sets – representing 13,743 children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A district health officer checks for a finger mark (indication of having received the measles vaccine) during RCM in a village in Nkhotakota. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;RCM results fed into an interactive online dashboard, accessible for those working on the campaign. (Special thanks to the British Red Cross for assisting with dashboard development!) CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each district had a daily meeting during the campaign to discuss daily activities. We sent the dashboard information ahead of time so that health officers would be aware of the website and could access the information. In the future, now that we have a smooth process for the technical side of this work, we would focus even more on building the local health staff’s awareness of the dashboard and their comfort in using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;role-of-missing-maps&quot;&gt;Role of Missing Maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For important base map data, we relied on the contributions of over 3,000 Missing Maps volunteers, who traced nearly 400,000 buildings across Malawi, equating to the homes of roughly 1.7 people. This data played an important role in planning our fieldwork and the logistics required. Additionally, the base data in OpenStreetMap was the background layer in the nationwide RCM dashboard, and for all our analytics and data visualizations. Without the many volunteers who contributed, the data collected would have simply been points on a blank canvas. Many thanks to all who helped with tracing in Malawi!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The paper map is not dead! Planning logistics and meet-up locations for social mobilization in Lilongwe. Map data from OpenStreetMap… made possible by Missing Maps volunteers. Thanks! CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170810_pic8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap data with social mobilization locations overlaid. The detail and quality of mapping across Malawi gave us high-resolution to examine and display results for both the RCM and social mobilization activities. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also grateful for Facebook’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ciesin.columbia.edu/data/hrsl/&quot;&gt;high-resolution population data&lt;/a&gt; for Malawi, which helped us to identify areas with and without concentrations of people. This made the tracing much, much faster – we filtered uninhabited areas out of the tracing tasks so that we could direct remote mappers towards areas that had features for them to map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have returned from Malawi, we are conducting data analysis and investigating possible support activities for a future campaign. We are excited to continue working with M&amp;amp;RI and look forward to implementing the lessons learned in this pilot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the mobile data collection activities, the GIS team is looking ahead to explore ways that we could use population and OSM data to inform logistical planning or population estimates for a vaccination campaign. We are eager to support as the Red Cross and the rest of the Measles &amp;amp; Rubella Initiative moves forward to combat measles and improve outcomes for children around the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Eros, Ashley Schmeltzer</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="POSM" /><summary type="html">Measles is one of the most contagious diseases ever known and it is a leading cause of death among children. In June, the American Red Cross supported a measles and rubella immunization campaign in Malawi that targeted nearly 8 million children.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Detailed drone and street-level imagery for mapping in the Philippines</title><link href="/blog/2017/07/27/drone-and-street-level-imagery-in-philippines/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Detailed drone and street-level imagery for mapping in the Philippines" /><published>2017-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/07/27/drone-and-street-level-imagery-in-philippines</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/07/27/drone-and-street-level-imagery-in-philippines/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;tindog-tabang-leyteño-stand-up-help-leyteños&quot;&gt;Tindog Tabang Leyteño (Stand Up, Help Leyteños)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the response to the disaster caused by Typhoon Haiyan (Yolanda), the strongest typhoon ever to make landfall in the Philippines, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redcross.org.ph/&quot;&gt;Philippine Red Cross&lt;/a&gt; in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redcross.org/about-us/our-work/international-services&quot;&gt;American Red Cross&lt;/a&gt; implemented Tindog Tabang Leyteño, a 3-year recovery project. The project covers 4 municipalities and 23 barangays. The main goal of the project is to contribute to building safe and resilient communities by identifying and addressing various factors that will help people sustainably rebuild their lives, livelihoods, and assets while ensuring that future climate, environmental, and disaster risks are addressed or minimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aerial-imagery-collection&quot;&gt;Aerial imagery collection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs), also known as Remotely Piloted Aircraft Systems (RPAS) or drones, are increasingly used for &lt;a href=&quot;http://drones.fsd.ch/en/drones-in-humanitarian-action/&quot;&gt;humanitarian purposes&lt;/a&gt;. Earlier this year, we leveraged drones for comprehensive aerial imagery collection to support the recovery program. High-resolution aerial imagery is a valuable resource when creating value-add information products for response, planning, monitoring, and resilience building activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_compare.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satellite vs drone imagery&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Resolution comparison between satellite imagery available on Google Maps (left) compared to drone imagery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coordination and legal aspects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When flying drones, it is important to comply with regulations, conduct activities professionally, and operate safely. Failing to do so could result in backlash against the future utilization of the technology. An FAA certified remote pilot from the American Red Cross GIS team as well as a volunteer that is certified were present for the project activities. During planning stages, we talked through the activities with the Philippine Red Cross. Then we communicated with all the local authorities to obtain their approvals. We then obtained all necessary authorizations from the Civil Aviation Authority of the Philippines (CAAP). Preparation for the trip was a several month process!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_slingshot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;POSM&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;When flying at 80 meters, kids with slingshots aren't much of a threat but maybe we should have done more information dissemination about our activities! CC-BY Matthew Marek&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took two fixed-wing drones, an &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Event38&quot;&gt;Event 38&lt;/a&gt; E384 and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TuffWing&quot;&gt;Tuffwing&lt;/a&gt; UAV Mapper, as well as a small quadcopter, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/djiglobal&quot;&gt;DJI&lt;/a&gt; Mavic Pro. Due to some technical challenges, and difficulties finding suitably large and clear areas for landing the fixed-wing drones, almost all our mapping ended up being with the Mavic. Because we had two pilots we ended up procuring a second Mavic after the first week to double our coverage speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_mavics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flying the Mavics&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;James McDanolds monitors a Mavic in flight while Dan Joseph troubleshoots another, CC-BY Ylla De Ocampo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-nL0WM8rgj4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Launching the Tuffwing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_training.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flying the Mavics&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;James McDanolds teaches Ylla De Ocampo from the Philippine Red Cross how to pilot the Mavic, CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ground control points&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tested using ground controls points (GCPs) in Barangay Marasbaras. We had 12 large fabric markers with distinct patterns that we placed around the area before collecting imagery. By using handheld Garmin GPS units’ waypoint averaging functionality, we could determine more accurate latitude and longitude coordinates for the markers which were then used after image processing to adjust and improve the accuracy of the final map products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_gcp2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ground control point&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One of the fabric markers used as a ground control point, CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_gcp1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;waypoint averaging&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Waypoint averaging with a Garmin GPS unit, CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_gcp3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;gcp visible in aerial imagery&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One of the GCPs visible in the aerial imagery, CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mapillary&quot;&gt;Mapillary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we travelled between barangays and walked around the areas, we used a variety of cameras to collect street-level imagery. The geotagged images collected with Sony action cameras, 360&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; cameras, and smart-phones were then uploaded to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapillary.com/&quot;&gt;Mapillary&lt;/a&gt; where they became part of an ever-growing, community built collection of openly licensed street-level images for the world. The images can provide valuable insights; it is possible to observe signage, the condition of buildings, and other aspects of the environment not visible in vertical aerial/satellite imagery. They allow anyone to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mapillary/status/874978591678791681&quot;&gt;#MapillaryExplore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_mapillary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;collecting mapillary&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hiding from the sun while &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapillary.com/app/?lat=10.859070004872933&amp;amp;lng=124.98645779947196&amp;amp;z=17&amp;amp;pKey=61GREpTo2sVH4BfhTSZm6A&amp;amp;focus=photo&amp;amp;x=0.3017540420440399&amp;amp;y=0.6072076945566833&amp;amp;zoom=0&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;collecting images&lt;/a&gt; with a 360&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; camera mounted on a pole&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;processing&quot;&gt;Processing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To process aerial drone imagery, we use an open-source toolkit called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDroneMap/OpenDroneMap#opendronemap&quot;&gt;OpenDroneMap (ODM)&lt;/a&gt;. ODM can combine the series of images captured during flight(s) over an area of interest into a single georeferenced image file that can be used for GIS purposes. We can perform this process in offline environments, having incorporated ODM into the set of software tools that we can run on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/posm/posm#posm&quot;&gt;POSM&lt;/a&gt; portable server. POSM runs on a small piece of hardware that is plugged into a power source and broadcasts a local wifi signal in order to connect devices. When connected to POSM, users can access several pieces of software, such as ODM and other mapping tools, that are normally cloud-based and require an internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_image-folder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;folder of images&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A folder full of the individual raw images collected over an area&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_posm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;POSM&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Processing imagery on a POSM, CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oam&quot;&gt;OAM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openaerialmap.org/&quot;&gt;OpenAerialMap (OAM)&lt;/a&gt; is a repository of openly licensed imagery and map layer services. We uploaded all the processed imagery to OAM so that it would be easily available for us, and others, to access and use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_oam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;OpenAerialMap&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Imagery on OpenAerialMap (OAM)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;openstreetmap&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OSM in the Philippines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a strong OSM-PH community and OSM is increasingly considered a useful source of geographic data in the Philippines. The Philippines government has recognized the strengths of OSM and its importance in creating “more accurate street-level risk analysis maps for the Philippines. This in turn will be used in improving disaster management before, during, and after emergencies” (&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.noah.dost.gov.ph/2016/04/08/map-your-community-in-osm-with-project-noah/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team (HOT) Tasking Manager&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To coordinate the digital volunteers helping to trace the project areas we used the Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team (HOT) Tasking Manager to divide each barangay up into a grid of tasks to be systematically traced and then validated by a skilled mapper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drone imagery, and the Mapillary images as well, proved useful for detailed, up-to-date tracing of map features into OSM. The improvements over what was possible using only satellite imagery are striking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_palanog-before.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;before&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Barangay Palanog 37-A before drone imagery was used to update &lt;a href=&quot;https://osm.org/go/44Cii0w6h--&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;OSM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_palanog-after.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;after&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Barangay Palanog 37-A after drone imagery was used to update &lt;a href=&quot;https://osm.org/go/44Cii0w6h--&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;OSM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We made all the imagery outputs available through &lt;a href=&quot;https://map.openaerialmap.org/#/125.32379150390624,10.875116370134366,9?_k=xfrwrc&quot;&gt;OAM&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapillary.com/app/?lat=11.061160979894737&amp;amp;lng=125.00135879610951&amp;amp;z=10&quot;&gt;Mapillary&lt;/a&gt;.
We’ve also made the raw datasets of aerial imagery &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1vX1C0k1TM0op9qQ0m8cXMUsMcUnzw3o7SE5dasOXbf8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;available&lt;/a&gt; with the intent that they can be used for purposes such as test datasets for the development of tools like ODM. You can check out the imagery in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://americanredcross.github.io/ttl-imagery/&quot;&gt;web viewer&lt;/a&gt;. The outputs will be shared with the communities and local government. The American Red Cross will continue to work with the Philippines Red Cross to utilize the data and think about future use of drones. We will continue to share and progress with our learning, and hopefully fly again soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170727_kids.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flying the Mavics&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Interested kids crowd around to see the screen displaying the status of one of the Mavics as it maps, CC-BY Ylla De Ocampo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Joseph</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Red Cross" /><category term="imagery" /><summary type="html">Earlier this year, the American Red Cross and Philippine Red Cross collected detailed aerial and street-level imagery of areas that have been part of a 3-year Typhoon Haiyan (Yolanda) recovery program.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">POSM 0.7: Faster and better than ever!</title><link href="/blog/2017/07/26/posm-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="POSM 0.7: Faster and better than ever!" /><published>2017-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/07/26/posm-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/07/26/posm-update/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;posm-07-faster-and-better-than-ever&quot;&gt;POSM 0.7: Faster and better than ever!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce a new and improved version of POSM – now faster and slicker than ever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on our experiences in the field, we made a number of improvements and fixes to help it meet our mapping needs more effectively. We’ve just released the updated system as POSM ~0.7.1 (codename: natural blowfish)~ 0.7.2 (codename: clear hen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additions and improvements include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Updates to the admin interface to make the user experience simpler and more straightforward, even as we add functionality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Built-in instruction manual. We wrote user-friendly documentation for the set-up and use of &lt;a href=&quot;http://posm.io/&quot;&gt;POSM&lt;/a&gt; and included it in the installer so that it’s available offline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added support for OpenDataKit’s data encryption features. Users can add a private key to their ODK form, upload the form to OpenMapKitServer on POSM, then download and decrypt the data using &lt;a href=&quot;https://opendatakit.org/use/briefcase/&quot;&gt;ODK Briefcase&lt;/a&gt;. This is part of our commitment to protecting sensitive information in the field. Getting started with ODK Briefcase can be a little confusing so we’ve added instructions &lt;a href=&quot;http://posm.io/in-the-field/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public file share now easier to find and use – no configuration changes necessary. Users can connect to POSM’s public file share to add files, apps, and other packages that they may need to share with volunteers or staff in the field&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selected software components updated (OSM’s iD editor, for example)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;POSM is now faster to install from a USB stick&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Various small bugs found and fixes applied&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170726_pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New POSM Admin interface&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;POSM's new admin interface makes the device easier to navigate and use. Offline instructions are linked on the left and the fileshare info is easy to find on the home screen. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170726_pic2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Online and offline instruction guide&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We wrote a step-by-step instruction guide where project managers can find everything they need to know about getting, setting up, and using a POSM. Troubleshooting tips are included and the full guide can be accessed [online](www.posm.io) or through the POSM itself. CC-BY American Red Cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POSM is ready for your offline enumeration, mapping, and imagery needs with its integration of OpenDataKit, OpenMapKit, Field Papers, OpenStreetMap, OpenDroneMap, and the POSM Imagery API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/posm/posm-build/releases&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and we encourage everyone using POSM to update their device(s) with this version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re excited about these improvements and hope you are, too!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Eros, Seth Fitzsimmons</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="POSM" /><summary type="html">We are pleased to announce a new and improved version of POSM – now faster and slicker than ever!</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Volunteers in Uganda and Turkey Rally to Support Refugees on World Refugee Day</title><link href="/blog/2017/07/10/world-refugee-day-2017/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volunteers in Uganda and Turkey Rally to Support Refugees on World Refugee Day" /><published>2017-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2017/07/10/world-refugee-day-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2017/07/10/world-refugee-day-2017/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-connects-kampala-and-istanbul&quot;&gt;What connects Kampala and Istanbul?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(originally posted to the Humanitarian OpenSteetMap Team &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hotosm.org/updates/2017-07-03_volunteers_in_uganda_and_turkey_rally_to_support_refugees_on_world_refugee_day&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on July 3, 2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What connects Kampala and Istanbul? You might be thinking that Kampala and Istanbul are worlds apart, but volunteers in both cities rallied around a common cause for World Refugee Day - working together to map priority areas in Uganda that require urgent humanitarian assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the protracted conflicts in Syria and South Sudan, displaced civilians continue to seek safety in neighboring countries and beyond. Turkey and Uganda have gained prominence on the world stage for opening their borders to receive refugees, particularly those fleeing from respective conflicts in Syria and South Sudan. More broadly, Turkey hosts the largest number of refugees in the world, with the UN High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) citing an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unhcr.org/statistics/unhcrstats/5943e8a34/global-trends-forced-displacement-2016.html&quot;&gt;estimated 2.9 million people in country in 2016&lt;/a&gt;. Uganda hosts the largest number of refugees in Africa, with over &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=57050#.WVEh0ROGOgQ&quot;&gt;1.2 million&lt;/a&gt; refugees and asylum seekers in country today. And these numbers continue to rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 2,000 people a day are crossing the border into Northern Uganda, with little more than they can carry. This has sparked a humanitarian emergency that the United Nations Secretary-General described as the “biggest refugee exodus since the genocide in Rwanda.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background-on-humanitarian-openstreetmap-team-and-the-refugee-crisis-in-uganda&quot;&gt;Background on Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team and the Refugee Crisis in Uganda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empowering refugees and host communities are key elements of the Ugandan national strategy to ensure self-reliance, resilience and accountability to displaced populations, in a context where refugees are unlikely to return to their countries of origin any time soon. National and district level authorities’ capacity should also be enhanced to provide assistance and deliver services to refugees in the same way it does for Uganda’s citizens. This is in recognition that national, regional and local authorities have the primary responsibility to assist refugees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team (HOT) in Uganda works in tandem with the local organization MapUganda to provide OpenStreetMap (OSM) tools, training, information management products and advisory services to humanitarian organizations working with refugees. HOT provides OSM tools to international organizations, local government and refugee communities, along with training, information management support and advisory services. Several volunteers are periodically trained to use OSM tools, and ready to support the humanitarian community with extensive data collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170710_map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Distribution of volunteers trained in using OSM tools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key partnerships with UNHCR, WFP and international NGOs ensure that OSM assistance contributes to build a common operating picture for the response to the refugee crisis, avoid duplications and provide timely informed decisions to implementing agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mappers-in-turkey-support-uganda-in-turkeys-first-missing-maps-mapathon&quot;&gt;Mappers in Turkey Support Uganda in Turkey’s First Missing Maps Mapathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To respond to the situation in Uganda, HOT and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sinirtanimayandoktorlar.org/&quot;&gt;Médecins Sans Frontières Turkey&lt;/a&gt; (MSF)organized Turkey’s First &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missingmaps.org/&quot;&gt;Missing Maps&lt;/a&gt; Mapathon in Istanbul on June 18, 2017. 38 volunteers gathered at Impact Hub Istanbul to pitch in and stand #WithRefugees, demonstrating how volunteers can provide remote mapping support to assist refugees and bring humanitarian assistance to the ground. As residents who sympathize with the plight of refugees in their own country, the event provided participants with a unique opportunity to understand a different context, to show solidarity, and to give back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants in Istanbul mapped 2,550 buildings in the Boroli, Olua and Ayilo Refugee Settlements, and completed 75% of the targeted region. They learned about Missing Maps, and HOT and MSF’s work. The majority of participants were new mappers, and were excited to learn about OSM and discover how they could contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170710_pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;All in a Day’s Work!&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;All in a Day’s Work: Volunteers show solidarity with refugees during Istanbul’s First Missing Maps Mapathon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170710_pic2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;People Live There!&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;People Live There! Istanbul Missing Maps Mapathon participants fill in &quot;blank spots&quot; on the map in the Boroli, Olua and Ayilo Refugee Settlements to facilitate humanitarian aid&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-istanbul-to-kampala-hot-uganda-organizes-mapathon-on-world-refugee-day&quot;&gt;From Istanbul to Kampala: HOT Uganda Organizes Mapathon on World Refugee Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170710_pic3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mapathon in Kampala&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Mapathon in Kampala&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 20, the HOT team in Uganda organized a mapathon in Kampala, with remote connection from MSF’s office in Yumbe, to contribute to the provisioning of up-to-date information on refugee settlements and hosting communities. The mapathon gathered several volunteers, humanitarian workers and representatives from UNHCR and WFP, and targeted mapping of shelters, main roads, boundaries for Maji Refugee Settlement and Adjumani Town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://arcmaps.s3.amazonaws.com/share/blog-pictures/missingmaps-blog_20170710_pic4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Opening of the Mapathon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Opening of the Mapathon in Kampala, HOT Country Manager with MapUganda colleagues&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gift of the United States Government - Bureau of Population, Refugees, and Migration - US Department of State.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Geoffrey Kateregga</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="HOT" /><category term="Turkey" /><category term="Uganda" /><summary type="html">What connects Kampala and Istanbul? You might be thinking that Kampala and Istanbul are worlds apart, but volunteers in both cities rallied around a common cause for World Refugee Day - working together to map priority areas in Uganda that require urgent humanitarian assistance.</summary></entry></feed>